http://youtu.be/GZnFAPGM9mw
Tung Dinh _ VGU http://youtu.be/GZnFAPGM9mw
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: So let's look at our software for our robot.
Ta sẽ tìm hiểu về code cho robot
The hardware is such that PB7-PB4 is to the right stepper.
Ta thiết lập chân PB7 tới PB4 cho motor phải
PB3 to PB0 is to the left.
PB3 tới PB0 cho trái
PE1 has the left bumper.
PE1 cho công tắc trái
PE0 has the right bumper, both positive logic.
PE0 cho công tắc phải, cả hai đều là positive logic
There's initialization, which is similar to all the other initializations we've
Đó là phần khởi tạo, tương tự như lúc trước từng làm
been doing so far, where port B is an output, port E is an input.
Port B là output, và port E là input
We will use a struct to define the components of a state.
Ta sẽ dùng 1 struct để xác định thành phần của 1 trạng thái
Each state will have an output, will have a time
Mỗi trạng thái sẽ có 1 output, có thời gian
to wait in 10 millisecond units, and four next states.
là 10 ms để đợi, và 4 trạng thái tiếp theo
Again, the four possible next states are zero zero means, we're OK.
Nhắc lại, 4 trạng thái tiếp theo 00, nghĩa là ok
Full speed ahead.
Chạy thẳng hết ga
Zero one means the right bumper just hit something,
01 nghĩa là công tắc phải bị nhấn
zero two means the left bumper hit something,
02 nghĩa là công tắc trái bị nhấn
and zero three means a head-on collision,
và 03 nghĩa là va chạm phía trước
both bumpers at the same time.
cả hai công tắc bị nhấn cùng lúc
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: So the indexes in this area respond to the inputs
Số 4 này tương đương với inputs
that you have to respond to.
phải phản hồi
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Absolutely.
Chính xác
An important thing about finite state machines, the reason it is so powerful
Một điều quan trọng nữa về máy trạng thái hữu hạn,
is because there is a one-to-one mapping between the structure that we drew,
là bởi cấu trúc 1-1 giữa các trạng thái ta vẽ
the state transition graph, and this data
đồ thị chuyển trạng thái, và cấu trúc này
structure that we will store in the computer.
ta sẽ lưu trong máy tính
Every state had exactly one output, every state had a time to wait,
Mỗi trạng thái chỉ duy nhất có 1 output, và chúng đề có thời gian chờ
and every state had four next states, shown here as indexes,
mỗi trạng thái có 4 trạng thái tiếp theo, biểu diễn ở đây
depending upon whether the input is zero, one, two, or three.
phụ thuộc vào input là 0 1 2 hay 3
So there is a one-to-one mapping.
Đó chính là cấu trúc 1-1
That means no more, no less information in this than the state transition
nghĩa là thông tin ở đây không hơn không kém đồ thị chuyển trạng thái
graph.
graph.
This data here completely specifies what the machine will do.
Dữ liệu ở đây hoàn toàn xác định được máy sẽ làm gì
We will store the current state in this variable called
Ta sẽ lưu trạng thái hiện tại trong biến này
cState, so will have a number between zero and nine
gọi là cState, nó sẽ có giá trị giữa 0 và 9
specifying the state number that we are currently in.
biẻu diễn trạng thái hiện tại
The initialization is to turn on the clock and the SysTick and the ports
Việc khởi tạo sẽ bật clock, SysTick và ports
and initialize the state to be the first state, or state zero.
và cũng khởi tạo trạng thái đầu tiên, trạng thái 0
And then we'll repeat the engine over and over again.
Ta cứ lập lại thôi
The first step is exactly like we saw with Dr. Yerraballi's, and that is,
Đầu tiên là y chang giáo sư Yerraballi đấy
we're going to output depending on the current state.
ta sẽ output ra phụ thuộc vào trạng thái hiện tại
So cState is our current state, and so we're
cState là trạng thái hiện tại
going to fetch the output field from that state and output it to port B.
và ta sẽ đưa output ra port B từ trạng thái đó
That will be one of the numbers we saw in the finite state machine.
Đó là 1 số ta thấy trong máy trạng thái hữu hạn
The next, to make it run at the speed we want,
Tiếp theo, để chạy với tốc độ ta muốn
is we were going to delay for a certain amount of time.
ta cần delay một khoảng thời gian
So a delay of two will mean it will wait 20 milliseconds.
delay 2 nghĩa là delay 20ms
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: So this will control
Vậy nó sẽ điều khiển
the speed at which the motors will rotate?
tốc độ motor quay?
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Yes.
Đúng vậy
So if we're waiting 20 milliseconds, that
Nếu ta đợi 20ms
will be 1.8 degrees for 20 milliseconds.
nó sẽ là 1.8 độ cho 20ms
Next, we'll fetch the input.
Kế đến là input
And so we're going to fetch the input from PORT E bit 0 and 1.
Ta sẽ đưa input từ Port E bit 0 và 1
And so this variable here is going to have the values zero, one, two,
Biến này đây sẽ có giá trị 0 1 2
or three, depending upon whether we hit something or not.
hoặc 3, phụ thuộc vào robot chạm cái gì hay không
And lastly, we're going to change state, depending
Cuối cùng, ta sẽ thay đổi trạng thái,
on both the input and the current state.
dựa vào cả input và trạng thái hiện tại
The current state will specify which one we're currently in,
Trạng thái hiện tại sẽ xác định
and then the input variable here, zero, one, two, or three,
và biến input ở đây 0 1 2 3
will specify what the next state will be,
sẽ xác định trạng thái tiếp theo là gì
depending on the input and the current state.
dựa vào input và trạng thái hiện tại
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: OK, let's look at the functioning
OK, giờ ta quan sát robot vận hành
of this robot in a real setting.
thực tế